Ajay Sharma

602, Royal Plaza 2, Beverly Park, Mira-Road(E), Thane-401107

Summary

I possess a diverse background with experience as a Data Analyst at Persistent Systems for 1.5+ years, specializing in analyzing present and historical people and business data. Additionally, I am engaged as a Data Science intern at SCAAI. My proficiency encompasses Data Wrangling, Data Modeling, and Data Visualization. I excel in providing comprehensive Exploratory, Perspective, and Predictive Data Analytics solutions.

Work Experience

Symbiosis Centre for Applied AI - SCAAI.

Research Intern Mar 2023 - Present

- o Completed online courses and self-study in machine learning, deep learning, and statistical modeling to expand knowledge in the field of Data Science.
- Developed and implemented machine learning models, including regression, classification in supervised, clustering in unsupervised models and Neural Networks (NNs) in Deep Learning.
- o Performed exploratory data analysis (EDA) to identify patterns and trends in large-scale data sets.
- Gained proficiency in deep learning techniques, implementing convolutional neural networks (CNNs) for image classification tasks.

Persistent Systems.

Associate Executive - Talent Analytics

Apr 2022 - Feb 2023

- Worked on the Analytics for the complete employee life cycle, analyzing current and past people & business data, providing actionable insights to the management.
- Automated the Reporting process using Excel, SQL, Python, Power BI, and Power Queries, reducing the reporting time by 80%.
- Worked with Talent Management team to develop the Annual Talent Planning (ATP) for the Financial Year 2022-23 and 2023-24.
- Achieved the hiring targets planning for the whole financial year for the organization according to the revenue targets.
- Created OLAP models, Power Queries, and Python scripts to visualize data from multiple data sources.
- Analyzed and presented the data to help the higher management formulate long and short-term strategies for the company.

Trainee - Talent Analytics

Sep 2021 - Mar 2022

- o Created monthly, weekly, and daily reports highlighting key performance data.
- Generated Ad-hoc reports according to the requirements.
- o Prepared and maintained Power BI Dashboards to track and forecast organizational KPIs.

PMS Robotics Research Center.....

R & D Intern - Robotics and Automation

Jan 2021 - May 2021

- o Worked on industrial projects, Research and Development, and Automation solution.
- Tasked with research and development of a system which can determine the quality of fruits and grade them accordingly.

Education

Symbiosis Institute of Technology B. Tech - Mechanical Engineering Pune

2021

Nirmala Memorial Foundation College of Commerce and Science

Mumbai

HSC - Science

2017

Projects

Cardiovascular Health Disease Prediction (June 2023 - Present).....

- o Project aims to develop a predictive model using machine learning techniques to estimate the ten-year risk of Coronary Heart Disease (CHD) for individuals based on various risk factors.
- o Comprehensive and cleaned dataset for CHD risk prediction.
- o Trained and validated machine learning models for CHD risk estimation.
- o Model interpretability reports, highlighting the significant risk factors.
- o GitHub Repository: Click here

Determination of Quality of Fruits using Thermal Image Processing (Jan 2021 - May 2021)...

- Developed a system to determine the quality of fruits and vegetables using captured thermal images.
- o Applied Image Enhancement, Thermal imaging, Image processing, Segmentation, and Edge Detection techniques to extract features contributing to fruit bruising or decay.

Predictive Maintenance of Ball Bearing (Jul 2020 - Dec 2020).....

- Predicted the life of a ball bearing model by generating data from a MATLAB-Simulink Digital Twin model.
- o Filtered noisy data and estimated remaining useful life using predictive maintenance tools.

Obstacle Detector Arduino Line Following Robot (Sep 2019 - Oct 2019).....

- o Designed a robot that follows a path by detecting a line marked on the ground.
- Adjusted the robot's direction of motion based on sensor outputs to keep it on the path.

SKILLS

Languages: SQL, Python

Tools: Power BI, Advanced Excel, Power Queries

Analysis: Business Analysis, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Statistics, EDA, Data Modelling,

ETL

Certifications & Courses

- o Full Stack Data Science Course: AlmaBetter, Dec 2022 Present
- o Microsoft Power BI Data Analyst Associate: Microsoft, Feb 2023
- Deep Learning Specialization DeepLearning.AI